Guide to the Disability Covid Chronicles Web Collection TAM.857
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Disability Covid Chronicles Web Collection
December 2020-October 2025
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mills, Mara
Kornstein, Harris
Rapp, Rayna
Ginsburg, Faye D.
Ruhl, Bella
TAM.857
156 websites in 156 archived websites.
Disability Covid Chronicles, a project compiled from 2020-2024 by New York University's Center for Disability Studies, aimed to document experiences of chronically ill and disabled people during the COVID-19 pandemic. The web collection contains their website; archived websites of other COVID-19 archive projects and disability resources; and their research, also known as fieldnotes. The fieldnotes include artwork, news articles, opinion pieces, social media posts, petitions, event listings, videos, photographs, art exhibitions, government documents, and toolkits.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Websites were selected by Shannon O'Neill through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession numbers associated with this collection is 2025.079 and 2025.097.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Historical Note
Disability Covid Chronicles was a project created by New York University's Center for Disability Studies, to document life for chronically ill and disabled people during the COVID-19 pandemic. Mara Mills, Harris Kornstein, Faye Ginsburg, and Rayna Rapp coordinated the project from 2020-2024, compiling digital materials for research for their book How to Be Disabled in a Pandemic. The Disability Covid Chronicles project considered disability to include "neurodivergence, aging, illness, mental disability, injury, and addiction," and those that might not use the term "disabled."
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series:
Series I: Disability Covid Chronicles
Series II: Resources
Series III: Fieldnotes
Scope and Contents
The Disability Covid Chronicles Web Collection (December 2020-October 2025) is made up of archived websites created and compiled by the Disability Covid Chronicles as part of the research for How to Be Disabled in a Pandemic and also to document the experiences of disabled and chronically ill during the COVID-19 pandemic from 2020-2024. Materials featured as "fieldnotes" include press releases on COVID-19 guidance during the pandemic; news articles about COVID-19 and Long COVID; social media posts; government documents; survival guides for people facing higher risk of COVID-19 or triage discrimation; videos; podcasts; publicity websites related to documentaries; recaps of virtual events; art exhibitions; and artwork. Other topics documented in the research include masking messaging; government watchdogs related to COVID-19; mutual aid; protest resources; subway accessibility; COVID-19 testing; wastewater and COVID-19 postivity tracking; vaccination; experiences of quarantine; remote work; unemployment; caregiving; and medical rationing. They also documented websites on "disability experiences including incarceration, low wage and essential work, maternal mental health, anti-Asian violence, senior centers, migrant detention centers, Long Covid, public schools, the MTA, blindness and digital accessibility, arts workers, and the Black Lives Matter protests." Alice Wong's work as disability rights activist during the COVID-19 pandemic is also well documented in the collection. Although the project was national in scope, many of the websites focus on the disability community in New York City. The majority of the collection focuses on COVID-19, but there is some materials related to the mpox outbreak in 2022-2023.
Users should be aware that materials in the collection discuss suicide and violence against disabled people. Materials in the collection also include ableist language, which has been maintained to convey the meaning and reclamation of the language by creators of the material.
COVID-19 (Disease); People with disabilities -- Civil rights; People with disabilities -- Political activity; New York University. Center for Disability Studies; Wong, Alice, 1974-
- Series I: Disability Covid Chronicles, July 2023-October 2025; 2 websites in 2 archived websites.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the main website for the Disability Covid Chronicles project and a YouTube video on the project from the NYU Center for Disability Studies.
  - Disability Covid Chronicles, July 2023-August 2025
  - Disability Covid Chronicles YouTube Video, October 2025
- Series II: Resources, August 2025; 22 websites in 22 archived websites
  Arrangement
  Series is arranged alphabetically by creator.
  This series contains the archived websites featured on the Resources page of the Disability Covid Chronicles website. The resources focus on other COVID-19 documentation projects and resources on disability in general.
  - Alternatives to Policing Based in Disability Justice, August 2025; Abolition and Disability Justice Collective
    Historical Note
    Alternatives to Policing Based in Disability Justice is an online zine by the Abolition and Disability Justice Collective advocating for abolition in carceral systems, such as in social work and psychiatric agencies.
    The website contains their guiding principles, translations, resources, events, and a glossary.
  - Disability & Covid-19, ADA National Network, August 2025; ADA National Network
    The website provides information about disability community rights under the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) and how they apply to COVID-19 and long COVID.
  - Long Hauling, August 2025; ArtsEverywhere
    Long Hauling "is a series of essays highlighting the stories of 'long COVID' survivors and community efforts to use the lessons learned from other viruses to provide care for patients during the early months of the outbreak and into the uncertainties of late-pandemic years."
  - The Breaking Point Project, August 2025; Breaking Point Project
    The Breaking Point Project is a storytelling and art platform for incarcerated disabled and chronically ill people.
  - Covid-19 and global mental health: Importance of cultural contexts, August 2025; Centre for Culture and the Mind
    The Covid-19 and Global Mental Health Project was established by researchers at the University of Copenhagen to explore "the emerging literature and debates about global mental health effects of the Covid-19 pandemic and related social isolation and economic downturn, asking how cultural and social difference is constructed and worked into the current mental health research."
  - Covid Disability Archive, August 2025
    The Covid Disability Archive is a repository of memorials, art, screenshots, texts, letters, videos, writing, memes, news stories, social media posts, and other materials that represent the experiences of chronically ill and/or disabled people during the Covid-19 pandemic.
  - Remote Access Archive, August 2025; Critical Design Lab
    The Remote Access Archive "documents the ways that disabled people and communities have used technology for remote forms of participation, both before and during the COVID-19 pandemic."
  - Crip Pandemic Life: A Tapestry, August 2025; Cultural Studies Association
    Special section of the Journal of the Cultural Studies Association's Lateral magazine. Articles focus on everyday life during the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - Exposed, August 2025; Daniel, Sharon
    Exposed, by Sharon Daniel, is a digital art project that documents the spread of COVID throughout the American carceral system. The project places audio clips and quotes by incarcerated people on a timeline of the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - DisArt, August 2025
    DisArt is an arts-centered nonprofit focused on creating and promoting disability culture.
    The website features podcast episodes.
  - Sick of It! A Disability Inside/Outside Project, August 2025; Fierce Invalids; Inside/Outside Collective
    Sick of It! is a solidarity group that works to build relationships between incarcerated disabled people and people in the free world.
    The website contains information on their pen pal program and issues of their zines.
  - #CripCOVID19Syllabus, August 2025; Hamraie, Aimi; Dolmage, Jay
    Syllabus of "first-person accounts of disabled, chronically ill, fat, Mad, Deaf, and crip experiences, activism, and thinking on the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic."
  - NYC Covid-19 Oral History, Narrative, and Memory Project, August 2025; Incite Institute
    An oral history project by sociologists, oral historians, and anthropologists at Incite and the Columbia Center for Oral History Research documenting New York City's experience of the pandemic.
  - COVID Collections Project, August 2025; Initiative for Critical Disaster Studies
    The COVID Collections Project is a collaboration among the Initiative for Critical Disaster Studies (NYU Gallatin), the Archives and Public History Program (NYU Graduate School of Arts and Sciences), and the E.L. Quarantelli Resource Collection at the University of Delaware's Disaster Research Center to catalog Covid documentation projects.
  - Voices of People with Disabilities During the COVID19 Outbreak, August 2025; International Disability Alliance
    Website featuring stories from disabled people internationally that share their experiences with the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - Creativity in the Time of COVID-19, August 2025; Michigan State University
    Creativity in the Time of COVID-19: Art as a Tool for Combating Inequity and Injustice (CTC-19) is a project of the Digital Humanities & Literary Cognition Lab at Michigan State University that documented how people were using creativity to cope with the pandemic.
    The website mostly contains information on their conference in 2024.
  - Autistic, Surviving and Thriving under COVID-19: Imagining Inclusive Autistic Futures, August 2025; Re•Storying Autism in Education
    The Re•Storying Autism in Education research project sought autistic and neurodivergent participants for an online digital zine-making workshop and research interviews about experiences of education and COVID-19 in October 2020.
  - Sick in Quarters, August 2025; Sick in Quarters Collective
    Sick in Quarters (SiQ) is a network of disabled and chronically ill artists and activists.
  - Autoethnographies of a Pandemic from Brooklyn's Epicenter, African American Intellectual History Society, August 2025; Theoharis, Jeanne; Entin, Joseph B.; Braswell, Dominick
    Article by Jeanne Theoharis, Joseph Entin, and Dominick Braswell in Black Perspectives.
  - COVID Ableism Narrative Archive Contact Form (UC Berkeley RadMadLab), August 2025; University of California, Berkeley
    Submission form for the COVID Ableism Narrative Archive at the University of California, Berkeley Disability Lab.
  - The Pandemic Journaling Project, August 2025; University of Connecticut
    The Pandemic Journaling Project is an opt-in project for everyday people to record journal entries on their COVID-19 pandemic experience four times a year.
  - High-Risk Pandemic Stories: A Syllabus, August 2025; Wong, Alice, 1974-
    Blog post on the Disability Visibility Project.
- Series III: Fieldnotes, December 2020-October 2025; 120 websites in 120 archived websites.
  This series contains the archived websites featured on the Fieldnotes page of the Disability Covid Chronicles website. The fieldnotes include artwork, news articles, opinion pieces, social media posts, petitions, event listings, videos, photographs, art exhibitions, government documents, and toolkits on experiences of disabled people during the COVID-19 pandemic. This research was collected by NYU Center for Disability Studies researchers from 2020-2024.
  - @kateisresting, August 2025
    Tweet starting the #AccessiblilityForAbleds hashtag.
  - 60 Minutes, September 2025; 60 minutes (Television program)
    Video of President Joe Biden on 60 Minutes.
  - Ackerman, Emily, August 2025
    Article by Emily Ackerman on COVID-19 isolation.
  - Al-Aly, Ziyad; Xie, Yan; Choi, Taeyoung, August 2025; Al-Aly, Ziyad
    Preprint on if nirmatrelvir lessens risk of Long COVID.
  - American Association of People with Disabilities, August 2025
    Press release by the American Association of People with Disabilities on the reduction in isolation guidance by the CDC.
  - AORTA (Anti-Oppression Resource and Training Alliance), August 2025
    Image containing the words "Disabled People Deserve to Live." The post calls for a public health strategy that includes disabled people.
  - Arielle, Zipporah, August 2025
    Article by Zipporah Arielle on Holocaust Remembrance Day during COVID.
  - Barbarin, Imani, August 2025
    TikTok video by Imani Barbarin on COVID-19 being a mass disabling event.
  - Benness, Brianne, August 2025
    Article by Brianne Benness on vaccine hesitancy for people with chronic illness.
  - Brooklyn Center for Independence of the Disabled, August 2025
    Photographs of members of the Brooklyn Center for Independence of the Disabled handing out KN95 masks and leaflets at Atlantic Terminal in Brooklyn.
  - California Care Rationing Coalition, September 2025
    Stacey Milbern on her concerns about care rationing as a ventilator user at a May 6, 2020 Press Conference with the California Care Rationing Coalition.
  - Center for Disease Control, August 2025
    CDC article on racial disparities in treatment of COVID-19 from 2022.
  - Centers for Medicare & Medicaid Services, August 2025; Centers for Medicare & Medicaid Services (U.S.)
    - Hospital-Acquired Condition Reduction Program, August 2025
      Information on the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid on a value-based-purchasing program to link inpatient hospital care with Medicare payments.
    - The Hospital Value-Based Purchasing (VBP) Program, August 2025
      Information on the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid to receive incentive patients for high quality of care in the inpatient hospital setting.
  - Chalkbeat, August 2025
    - "How remote learning upended instruction for NYC students with disabilities and their families", August 2025
      Article in Chalkbeat on remote learning for students with disabilities.
    - "NYC students with disabilities denied crucial services during remote learning, suit alleges", August 2025
      Article in Chalkbeat on lawsuit filed against New York City on owed special education student hours during the COVID pandemic.
    - "NYC gives the OK to shrink special education services amid coronavirus upheaval", August 2025
      Article in Chalkbeat on reducing special education services at the beginning of the COVID pandemic.
  - Chinese-American Planning Council, September 2025; Chinese-American Planning Council (New York, N.Y.)
    Graphic celebrating the 50th anniversary of Chinese-American Planning Council's Open Door Senior Center.
  - Contreras Maya, María Celina, August 2025; Contreras Maya, María Celina, 1967-
    Tweet thread about New York City subway station accessibility.
  - Critical Design Lab, August 2025
    Remote Access is a nightlife event for disabled people curated and designed by the Critical Design Lab.
    The website includes a participation guide for setting up a Remote Access party as well as event listings for previous events from 2020-2023.
  - Davids, JD, August 2025
    Blog post by JD Davids on people having the right to health despite being unvaccinated.
  - The Death Panel, August-September 2025
    The Death Panel is a podcast hosted by Beatrice Adler-Bolton, Artie Vierkant, Phil Rocco, and Jules Gill-Peterson on the "political economy of health."
    The website contains episodes and transcripts, as well as information on their Medicare for All Week of action in 2021.
  - de Freytas-Tamura, Kimiko, September 2025
    Article on protests against the Museum of Chinese in America.
  - Disability Rights Advocates, August 2025; Disability Rights Advocates, Inc.
    Press release from 2022 on disability advocates and the MTA signing a settlement agreement to make the subway 95% accessible by 2055.
  - Dolan, Gearóid, August 2025
    Website for The Biggest Obstacle, a documentary examining accessibility in the MTA subway system.
  - Downstate New York ADAPT, August 2025
    Photo of Downstate New York ADAPT protesters.
  - EV Grieve, August 2025
    Blog post by EV Grieve on the NYPD sweep of unhoused residents in the East Village. Includes interviews of the residents of "Anarchy Row."
  - Gaeta, Amy, August 2025
    Article by Amy Gaeta on virtual home building and rebuilding during the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - Gardiner, Finn, August 2025
    Article by Finn Gardiner on ableism and fatphobia during the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - Hinds, Carolyn, August 2025
    Article by Carolyn Hinds on the film industry and accessibility.
  - Ho, Sandy, August 2025
    Article by Sandy Ho on the Better Care Better Jobs Act.
  - Jackson, Monique, August 2025
    - Corona Diary Instagram, August 2025
      Instagram feed of Monique Jackson's graphic journal.
    - Still Ill: Corona Diary, August 2025
      Still Ill: Corona Diary is a graphic journal made up of a series of drawings documenting Monique Jackson's experiences after falling ill from a suspected infection of Covid-19 in March 2020.
  - Johnson, Cyree Jarelle, August 2025
    Article by Cyrée Jarelle Johnson on Black disability history.
  - Long COVID Justice, August 2025
    - Commit to Long COVID Justice, August 2025
      Pledge on committing to justice for Long COVID.
    - Long COVID Justice Instagram, August 2025
      Instagram feed for the Long COVID Justice grassroots organization. Includes posts on resource sheets and events.
    - Long COVID Justice Valentines, August 2025
    - "Pandemics Are Chronic", August 2025
      Statement by Long COVID Justice on prioritizing chronically ill and disabled people beyond the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - Mariani, Mike, August 2025
    Article in the Guardian on the acceptance of Long COVID as a health condition.
  - Mugrabi, Sunshine, August 2025
    Article in Rooted in Rights by Sunshine Mugrabi.
  - Myalgic Encephalomyelitis Action Network, August 2025
    - 2022 #MillionsMissing Newsletter, August 2025
      Newsletter on the 2022 #MillionsMissing protest.
    - #MillionsMissing Our Demands, August 2025
      Letter from the Myalgic Encephalomyelitis Action Network calling for President Biden to declare Long COVID and myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome a national emergency.
    - Postcards to Doctors, August 2025
      Postcard campaign by the Myalgic Encephalomyelitis Action Network to encourage United States doctors to take a course on myalgic encephalomyelitis.
  - National Federation of the Blind, August 2025
    - Letter Regarding the Accessibility of At-Home COVID-19 Tests and Test Requests (January 3, 2022), August 2025
      Letter to the President of the United States from the National Federation of the Blind on making at-home COVID tests accessible to blind people.
    - Letter to FDA Commissioner Regarding Accessible Instructions for At-Home COVID-19 Test Kits (February 4, 2022), August 2025
      Letter to the Commissioner of the United States Food and Drug Administration from the National Federation of the Blind on creating accessible at-home COVID tests for blind people.
  - NBC News, August 2025
    NBC News article on the rollout of the Mpox vaccine.
  - New York Office of the Mayor, August 2025; New York (N.Y.). Office of the Mayor
    Press release from the New York City mayor's office.
  - New York Governor, December 2020-October 2025; New York (State). Governor; Cuomo, Andrew M., 1957-
    Press release and video on closure of non-essential businesses at the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic.
  - New York State Assembly, August 2025; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly
    - New York State Assembly Bill A5367A, August 2025
      Bill that removes "certain restrictions on eligibility for personal and home care services under Medicaid."
    - New York State Assembly Bill A7712B, August 2025
      Bill that "provides for a myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome education and outreach program."
  - New York City Public Schools, August 2025
    Includes New York City Public Schools updates to COVID-19 Health and Safety Protocols in 2021.
  - New-York Historical Society, August 2025
    Exhibit at the New-York Historical Society on the history of homelessness and artist and activist response in the 1980s and 1990s.
  - NoBody Is Disposable Coalition, August 2025
    A toolkit that covers rights and strategies for people facing potential triage discrimination based on disability or weight, alone or in combination with other characteristics, during the COVID-19 pandemic in the United States.
  - NY1, August 2025
    NY1 report on COVID sub-variant JN.1.
  - Ocula, August 2025
    Article in Ocula about the CRIP TIME exhibit at the MMK Museum für Moderne Kunst in Frankfurt, Germany.
  - Open Doors NYC
    Open Doors NYC is a collective of nursing home residents, advocates, and allies who work through art and activism. Their projects include documentaries, poetry anthologies, plays, professional development workshops, a podcast, and weekly events.
    - Meet The Reality Poets, August 2025
    - Open Doors NYC, August 2025
      The website includes a Nursing Home Bill of Rights.
    - Fire Through Dry Grass, August 2025
      Fire Through Dry Grass is a documentary by Alexis Neophytides and Andres "Jay" Molina on nursing home residents on Roosevelt Island during the COVID-19 pandemic.